<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Craig Edmunds]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.ctoaas.co/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.ctoaas.co/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-14T16:40:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.ctoaas.co/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ctoaas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doing agile badly]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ctoaas.co/blog/2013/10/14/doing-agile-badly/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-14T07:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ctoaas.co/blog/2013/10/14/doing-agile-badly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve seen a number of teams who proclaim to be &lsquo;doing agile&rsquo;, with varying levels of success. For me, and especially where the team isn&rsquo;t in a complex environment (i.e. a hierarchy of agile teams / scrums of scrums, etc), the major benefit of agile is that it allows the team to be as efficient as possible, delivering as much business value as possible.</p>

<p>Agile is often used as a positive spin on disorganised, and this actually accerbates the problem; both through the differences between reality and what is presented to customers, prospective team members and other stakeholders, and because of the additional process and work associated with agile (retrospectives, planning sessions) that are ineffective and waste time when not used properly.</p>

<p>Below are some common traits I&rsquo;ve seen in good teams, and how to spot when they may not be correct, I&rsquo;ve often seen the opposite of these in teams and when you talk to individuals in the team you&rsquo;ll often hear complaints, moaning and general disatisfaction.</p>

<ul>
<li>The team either has an empowered sponsor/business owner available at least 80% of the time, or there is a good understanding of the acceptance criteria for work items being delivered. If you regularly have situations where the sponsors expectations aren&rsquo;t met, this is likely to be the issue.</li>
<li>The backlog is managed sensibly, with work coming into the backlog and the team managing it through the process. Work coming in directly to individuals is a common indication this isn&rsquo;t happening.</li>
<li>Work item estimation is done with a good understanding of what the scope / acceptance criteria are. Estimating based on a one line description are unlikely to be accurate.</li>
<li>The team has an appropriate development process for their situation. If the team is less than ten people, in one room, a simple wall board should suffice. If you have remote team members you need to think about how they interact with it.</li>
<li>The team is empowered to deliver, and to modify their development process. This should be handled in the retrospective with the team optimising as appropriate.</li>
<li>The team has a culture of code quality, especially tests. You often see a reluctance to refactor code when a codebase has insufficient tests.</li>
<li>The team has an engaged daily standup with a small amount, but not too much, back and forth between team members. A flat, boring update with everyone giving a 15 second update to the team leader doesn&rsquo;t really add value.</li>
<li>The team regularly contribute to each others features, through discussion, review, pairing and testing. A group of people working in isolation does not equal a team.</li>
<li>The team ships regularly, whether this is to a UAT envvironment, or live features are being deployed regularly. If the shorter of a month, or two iterations go by and this hasn&rsquo;t happened, it&rsquo;s a bad sign.</li>
</ul>


<p>Do you recognise any of them in your team?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up a simple blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ctoaas.co/blog/2013/09/22/setting-up-a-simple-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T21:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ctoaas.co/blog/2013/09/22/setting-up-a-simple-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of a new business I&rsquo;m setting up, I wanted to get a simple blog system online. In the past I&rsquo;ve used Wordpress, and although I hate PHP have never found anything that made sense as an alternative.</p>

<p>For me the criteria for an alternative were :
&ndash; Written in a language platform I was interested in &ndash; this is pretty much any common, current web stack, except PHP.
&ndash; Feature rich with the ability to extend it, an abundence of extensions and an active community.
&ndash; Has a straightforward and cheap cloud deployment mechanism.</p>

<p>But thinking about it again recently I&rsquo;m more interested in:
&ndash; Has a straightforward and cheap cloud deployment mechanism.
&ndash; Very little maintenance requirement &ndash; a static deployment to S3 would be perfect
&ndash; Allowing the post content to be edited locally in text files, in an open format
&ndash; Have a number of themes available, so that I only need to pick one and write some content and off I go
&ndash; This is less of a priority but I&rsquo;m using node JS on a project I&rsquo;m working on at the moment, which I&rsquo;m new to, so any coding (extensions, templates, etc) being in Javascript would be ideal</p>

<p>This led me towards Blacksmith, <a href="https://github.com/flatiron/blacksmith,">https://github.com/flatiron/blacksmith,</a> using an S3 static website for the hosting. I was pretty close to moving forward with this, but couldn&rsquo;t find much in the way of themes. I&rsquo;ve now settled (I think) on Octopress, and probably github pages for the hosting. I have a basic understanding of Ruby, and haven&rsquo;t used it in anger &ndash; but I assume I&rsquo;ll be able to pick it up should I need to.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll now document the install process from my Mac.</p>

<p>I started by following these articles:</p>

<pre><code>http://miguelcamba.com/blog/2013/04/22/tutorial-create-a-blog-with-octopress-and-host-it-in-github-pages/
</code></pre>

<p>The first issue I received was when running rake deploy, which returned this error:</p>

<pre><code>"You have already activated rake 10.1.0, but your Gemfile requires rake 0.9.2.2. Using bundle exec may solve this."
</code></pre>

<p>Running &ldquo;bundle exec rake install&rdquo; fixed this.</p>

<p>The same went for the next few bundle commands, resolved using:</p>

<pre><code>bundle exec rake setup_github_pages
bundle exec rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>When running this deployment task I received the error:</p>

<pre><code>## Pushing generated _deploy website
To -- removed for security --
 ! [rejected]        master -&gt; master (non-fast-forward)
error: failed to push some refs to '-- removed for security --'
hint: Updates were rejected because the tip of your current branch is behind
hint: its remote counterpart. Merge the remote changes (e.g. 'git pull')
hint: before pushing again.
</code></pre>

<p>One tip &ndash; when creating the repo in github, don&rsquo;t specify a git ignore or a licence and this issue seems to be avoided. I did find a solution to this on stack overflow : <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/17609453/rake-gen-deploy-rejected-in-octopress">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/17609453/rake-gen-deploy-rejected-in-octopress</a></p>

<pre><code>Edit the Rakefile and look for this line:

system "git push origin #{deploy_branch}"
Alter the line by adding a plus (+) before the #{deploy_branch} tag:

system "git push origin +#{deploy_branch}"
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
